Good morning, it says starting dot dot dot. Good morning. Today is
the 10th of אדר, Adar, it's February 25th, Sunday morning. And Rabbi
Linzer is still in Israel. I'm Dan Margules and I'll fill in
for him today. We are going to pick up, we just started
the third פרק Perek of מסכת עבודה זרה Masechet Avodah Zarah last
night. It was שבת, Shabbat, so it wasn't recorded. But we will
pick up at the bottom of מ"מ עמוד ב', Mem Amud Bet,
where we have the discussion, the משנה Mishnah had discussed a three-way
מחלוקת Machloket about which types of statues are under the presumption that
they are statues of עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah, that is that they're
actually worshipped rather than just having been constructed for decoration. And our
גמרא Gemara is exploring some of those details. So we're picking up
from the second to last line of מ"מ עמוד ב'. Mem Amud
Bet. אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל: Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Shmuel: באנדרטי
של מלכים שנינו. be'andarti shel melakhim shaninu. The משנה Mishnah is referring
to a case of when the statue is made of in the
form of the king, let's say. רש"י Rashi says: כשהמלך מת עושין
צורתו בפתח השער לזכרון. keshehamelakh met osin tzurato bepetach hasha'ar lezikaron. They
put the king's statue at the entrance of the city so as
to commemorate the king. And that is with regard to how do
you know whether this statue is or is not worshipped based on
the signs of what it's holding in its hand or not and
things like that. We had already, basically the first סוגיא Sugya in
the גמרא, Gemara, very short, had rejected the position of רבי מאיר,
Rabbi Meir, or had explained why the other Rabbis do not accept
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir's stringency. אמר רבה בר בר חנה אמר רבי
יוחנן: Amar Rabba bar Bar Chana amar Rabbi Yochanan: בעומדים על פתח
מדינה שנינו. be'omdim al petach medinah shaninu.
And it refers specifically to when the statue of the king is
placed at the entrance of the city. אמר רבא: Amar Rava: מחלוקת
בשל כפרים. Machloket beshel kefarim.
We're talking specifically about in small towns. That so this is a
different take on our משנה, Mishnah, not that it's referring specifically to
statues of the king at the entrance of the city, but that
the מחלוקת תנאים Machloket Tanna'im is about statues which are present in
a small town, in a village. אבל בשל כרכים דברי הכל מותרים.
Aval beshel kerakhim divrei hakol mutarin. But everyone agrees that statues that
are found in the city rather than in a village are permissible.
מאי טעמא? Mai ta'ama? What's the reason why? לנוי עבדי להו. Lenoi
avdei lehu. The reason why is in cities they're made for beautification
of the city. There's a sense of a municipal beautification project to
put up statues, but in a small village where there are less
municipal funds, there's more of a sense that the statues were erected
to be worshipped. So that's basically the difference in presumption. ובכפרים מי
איכא מאן דאמר לנוי קא עבדי להו? Uvikhfarim mi ika man de'amar
lenoi ka'avdei lehu?
In small villages we don't, nobody says that they put them up
for לנוי, Noi, for beautification. דכפרים ודאי דמפלחין הוא עבדי להו. Dikfarim
vadai demefalchin hu avdei lehu.
So the reason why is obviously that in villages they put up
statues in order to worship them, in order to bow down to
them. אלא איתמר הכי איתמר. Ella, itmar hachi itmar. You should say
it like this. אמר רבא: Amar Rava: מחלוקת בשל כרכים. Machloket beshel
kerakhim. רבא Rava says rather the משנה Mishnah must be referring to
cities specifically. אבל בשל כפרים דברי הכל אסורים. Aval beshel kefarim divrei
hakol asurin. That the מחלוקת Machloket refers to in cities, not that
everyone agrees everything in a city is permissible, because that would be
too extreme. But to say that in the city is the מחלוקת
תנאים Machloket Tanna'im and in the villages everyone agrees that every statue
is prohibited. So now we've cleared up a little bit what our
משנה Mishnah is talking about. Okay. וחכמים אומרים אינן אסורים. Ve'chakhamim omrim:
einan asurin. So the Rabbis, the consensus rabbinic position, the middle position
in our משנה Mishnah says it's only prohibited those statues which are
holding a מקל, makkel, a staff, a scepter, a ציפור, tzippor, a
bird, or a כדור, kaddur, a ball, a globe.
Okay, so we have to clarify what's the symbolism of each of
these, why are these indicative that the statue was meant to be
worshipped. מקל: Makkel: שרודה את עצמו תחת כל העולם כולו כמקל. she'rodeh
et atzmo tachat kol ha'olam kulo kemakkel.
It's like the statue is presenting himself as if ruling over the
world with a scepter, with a staff. You'll see part of the
difficulty with this גמרא Gemara is that many of the lines are
in written in inverted euphemistic language. So the word תחת tachat here
is kind of here saying he rules, רודה את עצמו תחת. rodeh
et atzmo tachat. It should be רודה את עצמו על כל העולם
כולו, rodeh et atzmo al kol ha'olam kulo, that he rules over
the world. But they put it under to actually to make fun
of the idol, to say that the idol is being suppressed underneath
because it's a false god. So those kind of, the Rabbis use
these inverted euphemisms, sometimes it's difficult to pay attention, you could get
lost. ציפור: Tzippor: why what about a holding a bird? שתופס את
עצמו תחת כל העולם כולו כציפור. shetofes et atzmo tachat kol ha'olam
kulo ketzippor. We mentioned yesterday many of these pagan depictions would show
the god holding a falcon or an eagle or something, hawk or
something like that, to show that he has control over the earth
like you train a bird. So that's the same kind of symbolism.
כדור: Kaddur: שתופס את עצמו תחת העולם כולו ככדור. shetofes et atzmo
tachat ha'olam kulo kekaddur. that he is able to hold support the
whole world like a ball. There is a if you actually study
the mathematicians from the Greek era it's pretty clear that that people
were aware that the earth was a sphere or spheroid, their calculations
of the radius of the earth they already go back to the
Greek times, but then at some point it it got lost or
people were not so aware of it and there were misconceptions that
spread, but certainly in Columbus's time where people say oh Columbus proved
the world the earth is round, it's not true, everybody already knew
the earth was round.
The question he he didn't get the circumference correct.
Right, he didn't get the circumference correct, whatever they didn't have good
measurements of those sorts of things. But anyway, so כדור Kadur obviously
in in time of תנ"ך Tanach there was more of a sense
that the earth was sort of a flat disc and things like
that, but we could discuss that another time. Okay, ככדור. K'kadur. תנא
Tana הוסיפו עליהם Hosifu aleihem
so then later, that is beyond what's listed in the משנה, Mishna,
the ברייתא Braita adds other examples of things which a statue could
be holding, which would make it indicative that it's עבודה זרה Avoda
Zara and what is that? הוסיפו עליהם Hosifu aleihem they added to
that סייף Sayif a sword, עטרה Atara a crown, וטבעת V'tabaat and
a ring. These are other signs of either military might or or
royal rule which would be would be a way of demonstrating that
the statue is not just erected in honor of some person or
even as a beautification, but is erected as a memorial as a
as an object of worship to demonstrate that this god rules over
whatever. Yeah.
The intent in making the idol rather than whether or not it
is actually
I don't think it's that it's the intent in making it, it's
that once it was made a certain way the presumption is that
the people will treat it a certain way. If it's made with
these sort of iconic imagery, it's clear that that the person who
made it and the person who commissioned it and the people who
live there are all going to be treating it as עבודה זרה.
Avoda Zara. I think that's sort of the presumption. And again, this
sort of this is a presumption. The point that we saw yesterday
was that well if you know that they worship it, then then
even even if it doesn't hold any of these things it should
be a problem.
These are just, you know you walk into a city you've never
been to before and I see a statue on the street, you
know and it's it's you know George Washington on a horse. Well
is George Washington on a horse, is that עבודה זרה, Avoda Zara,
is it אסור בהנאה? Assur b'hana'ah? So now I know the presumption
is that George Washington on a horse is just for beautification of
the city. No no American person goes to George Washington and and
pours a libation of wine on the ground or anything like that.
But what if it's George Washington holding a staff on a horse?
Okay, so maybe then what we have is there's a presumption but
maybe the presumptions have changed or the right these kinds of questions.
What color was George Washington's bronze horse? White horse?
You don't really answer that question though. What color was George Washington's
white horse? What color? Can you guess? White? Nope. That's the wrong
answer. The answer is roan because because according to taxonomy a horse
can't be classified as white and it's considered some shade of roan,
that's how the whole joke starts. Because it's a white horse, but
it's not considered white.
There you go. So that's not even a joke, that's like an
un-joke. Yeah.
But so the more interesting question would be would Stone Mountain Georgia
be a עבודה זרה?
Avoda Zara? נוהגים בהם אלוהות? Nohagim bahem elohut? Yeah, all these and
Mount Rushmore and all other kind of things. Okay. Okay, so now
we're going to clarify. So סייף, Sayif, so why did they change
their mind about a sword? סייף Sayif מעיקרא סבור ליסטים בעלמא. Me'ikara
savur listim be'alma. At the beginning when they they used to see
a statue holding a sword they said oh it's just a demonstration
that this is a bandit, that this is some military violent person.
ולבסוף סבר שהורג את עצמו תחת כל העולם כולו. U'levasof savar she'horeg
et atzmo tachat kol ha'olam kulo. And then they inferred that actually
it's demonstration that the idol is presenting himself as if he can
kill everyone in the whole world. Obviously here the תחת, Tachat, הורג
את עצמו, Horeg et atzmo, he'll kill himself. It doesn't mean kill
himself, it means kills everyone else. עטרה Atara מעיקרא סבור גדיל כלילי
בעלמא. Me'ikara savur gidil kelili be'alma.
So originally they thought that the crown was demonstrative of just that
that someone someone made a crown, right? רש"י Rashi says, אומן שם
לו עטרה Uman sam lo atara that that some craftsman made a
crown for the for the idol. ולבסוף סבר כעטרה למלך. U'levasof savar
k'atara lamelech.
It's like a crown of the king, that is to show mastery,
to show rule. טבעת, Tabaat, what about a a ring? מעיקרא סבור
אשתימא בעלמא. Me'ikara savur ishtima be'alma.
So originally they thought it was just to to to demonstrate that
right when the king appoints the grand vizier, this is coming up
obviously עניינא דיומא Inyana deyoma this week, right? When אחשוורוש Achashverosh appoints
המן Haman and then he appoints מרדכי Mordechai to be his his
grand vizier, he gives him the signet ring, that is the I'm
empowering you to sign my name on all of the official documents,
right? So originally they thought though it just means oh it's a
demonstration that this idol was is right doing the שליחות Shlichut of
whoever sent him. That it's not actually a demonstration that it's a
worshiped idol. ולבסוף סבר שחותם את עצמו תחת כל העולם כולו למיתה.
U'levasof savar she'chotem et atzmo tachat kol ha'olam kulo l'mita. They interpreted
it later to mean that the idol presents himself as if he
seals the whole world for death. having life and death control, to
sign over, to seal over everyone to death. And that, of course,
we are very familiar with an imagery of sealing people for life
or for death. That's our image of יום כיפור Yom Kippur that
God is there with the royal decree pressing the royal stamp and
obviously our Midrashic tradition tells us חותמו של הקדוש ברוך הוא אמת.
chotamo shel hakadosh baruch hu emet. The seal God's signet seal is
truth, whatever that means, that could be parsed in many different ways,
but it's an important concept.
So I want to understand what the אביי Abaye is about a
scythe that they thought, meaning they thought that
originally it was just a statue of the bandit king or whatever,
meaning to show, oh look, I'm a great military leader or whatever,
but then the interpretation is either local: this king shows himself to
be a king, shows himself to be powerful regional ruler and that's
why he made a statue of himself, or is it presents himself
as having cosmic powers, able to kill everyone in the whole world,
able to make decrees over everyone in the whole world, then that's
setting himself up as עבודה זרה. Avodah Zarah. And Charlie is showing
a picture of
a statue of Jupiter,
a statue of Jupiter with a staff and an eagle and something
else.
Yeah, the eagle is sitting next to him. Oh, the ball. So
there you go, all three.
Where is this? It is now in Russia.
There you go.
Not clear exactly what it's doing in Russia but
there you go, perfect example.
We'll put this onto the video there.
Okay, first century Common Era. First century Common Era. Okay.
So now it's clear, yes, is it an image of at least
Queen Elizabeth on a stamp where she's holding a sphere and a
stamp?
Right, because the scepter, the globe and the scepter are signs, but
that's what's important is that the shift, and that's what's sort of
being demonstrated here, is there's a shift between a mindset of this
demonstrates royal rule, and then when it's erected posthumously or when it's
erected in a certain pose or in a certain way and in
a certain cultural context, the presumption shifts not that it's a demonstration
of royalty, but it's a demonstration of divinity, that it's that this
person depicted in this statue actually has the power to kill everyone
in the world or to rule over the whole world or whatever.
So that symbolism is the iconography of the time and place. So
these kinds of presumptions, I think if you would ask nowadays, does
every statue that's sculpted with a person holding a falcon on their
wrist, oh, it means it's עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah and it's אסור
בהנאה, assur behana'ah, even in our משנה? Mishnah? I don't think it
was necessarily...
I think nowadays things are entirely different.
I don't think that these are all חזקות, chazakot, they're all presumptions
and assumptions that you can make presumably and again maybe this is
much debated, but how much you have to reassess the evaluation of
those kinds of presumptions under having new information. We know now that
basically all sculptures, basically in our society, in our part of the
world, basically all sculptures are created לנוי, lenoy, they're created as artwork.
There are some which are worshiped and you have to be careful
of those and usually they're depictions of particular people or particular types
of beings and then you keep your eyes out for that. But
in general a sculpture, even a representational sculpture of a human being,
which is אסור assur for a Jewish person to own and אסור
assur for a Jewish person to make, but is not necessarily meant
as an עבודה זרה. Avodah Zarah. So anyway, we'll continue.
So
perhaps the imagery of the sovereign king holding that is just as
a representative of a God.
Well, there are all different ways to parse it. Right, down. Yeah,
well, that's what sort of how רש״י Rashi is parsing it as
well.
Yeah, exactly, kings show themselves as representatives of God.
Right,
well, that's what רש״י Rashi is saying about the חותם, chotam, right?
The חותם chotam is also a sign that oh they have a
different picture here. Okay, we have now the opinion of רבן שמעון
בן גמליאל, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel, רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon
ben Gamliel says תנא אפילו צרור אפילו קיסם. tana afilu tzror afilu
keysam.
So adding on to the opinion of רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban
Shimon ben Gamliel who says even holding anything in his hand, even
a צרור, tzror, a stone, and אפילו קיסם, afilu keysam, even a
splinter of wood that is totally meaningless or low quality or cheap
object, you might say like, 'Oh, why did you sculpt this sculpture
of this person holding a stick?' is to show or a splinter
of wood is sort of to say like, 'Oh, it's actually degrading
to them' but רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel is
of the opinion it's actually anything is meant as an object of
worship. So by רב אשי, Rav Ashi, רב אשי Rav Ashi asked
תפס בידו צואה מהו, tafas beyado tzoa mahu,
what if the statue...
Did you really see like a statue with that
or is he just being difficult? No, I think I think and
again maybe I'm being a little bit too modernish in my thinking.
I think when the Rabbis talk about בעל פעור, Baal Peor,
I think and I could be corrected here and I'm happy to
learn there was such a real cult like this, as far as
I understand it's meant as an exaggerated נפקא מינא nafkamina case. בעל
פעור Baal Peor is the constructed עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah the Rabbis
imagine that was worshiped. worshipped by defecating in front of the idol.
So, in that case, you would say, oh, well, isn't that degrading?
Isn't this, it's not really a real mode of worship? You say,
no, we use that to define the extreme of what what is
the limit of what's considered if it's the worship of this idol,
then then even if it's incredibly degrading and disgusting, it's still something
which would be a prohibited. So, that's sort of used as a
test case and מרקוליס Markulis as well, which actually is a real
god, but the the rabbis depict the worship of the Roman god
Mercury not by placing stones on a cairn of stones and building
them out, but throwing rocks at the idol to destroy it. So,
it's also becomes a destructive or degrading kind of worship. So here
too I think רב אשי'ס Rav Ashi's question of oh, רבן שמעון
בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel said if the idol's statue is
holding anything in its hand you should assume it's an idol. So
רב אשי Rav Ashi said: What's the farthest extreme I can ask?
If he's holding human waste in his hand. So the assumption is
whether that do you take it to the full extreme or would
רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel even admit actually a
statue which is holding human waste in his hand is demonstratively not
an necessarily assumed to be an idol. Now why anyone would carve
such an idol is a separate... That's what I'm saying. Right. So,
מהו מי אמרינן כולי עלמא זיל באפי כצואה, mahu mi amrinan kuli
alma zil be'apei katzoa, so basically that that maybe what it's
demonstrating is that this this god treats everything else in creation like
like human waste, like waste in front of him. That is, that
they're considered so lowly in comparison to him, so that could still
be a demonstration of the divinity of the idol. So
איכא דאמרי הוא מהו דתימא דאזיל באפי כולי עלמא כצואה תיקו. ika
d'amri hu mahu de'teima de'azil be'apei kuli alma katzoa teiku. Or do
we say that it means he treats himself in front of everyone
else like waste, that is that it's actually degrading.
Why would someone carve
a statue to worship
that... Not to worship, that's the point, that it wouldn't be for
worship. It would be yeah, I make an insulting statue of my
enemies and I show them holding holding waste in their hand. Right.
You could imagine such a culture would that be people might...
I think, you know, I think that if there's a baby carved
nearby... Oh, I don't know if that changes the context...
Okay, תיקו. teiku. So the question was left unanswered. So it's interest
the point is רב אשי Rav Ashi many generations later asked a
question to try to develop some precision in רבן שמעון בן גמליאל'ס
Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel's position, how far should he take it, and
it was the question was left unresolved. Okay. But since the הלכה
halacha does not follow רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel
anyway, seemingly, it shouldn't matter. But actually the fact that רב אשי
Rav Ashi asked that question might be an indication that at least
רב אשי Rav Ashi may have thought the הלכה halacha should follow
רבן שמעון בן גמליאל. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel. But that's interesting. Okay,
next משנה. mishna. המוציא שברי צלמים, hamotzi shivrei tzelamim, a
person who finds broken statues. הרי אלו מותרים, harei elu mutarim, you
can assume that the fact that they're broken means that they're no
longer prohibited because of עבודה זרה. avoda zara. מצא תבנית יד או
תבנית רגל, matza tavnit yad o tavnit regel, but if you find
it in the shape of a hand or in the shape of
a foot. הרי אלו אסורים. harei elu asurim.
Like you found like a part of a leg?
Like you find...
You see that all the time now in statues, remnants...
Oh I'm a terrible artist... Okay so you find just the foot,
right? Where the monsters are, where the waftlings are, right? Something like
that. So if you find just the foot, then then that's that
would be prohibited. Why? So אלו אסורים מפני שכיוצא בהן נעבד, elu
asurim mipnei shekayotzei bahen ne'evad, because there are some deities that are
worshipped only they only make a representation of the hand of the
god or of the foot of the god or something like that.
So that would also be problematic. You have to assume that it
would still be problematic as עבודה זרה. avoda zara. אמר שמואל... amar
shmuel...
And note that the image,
the fragments of the images are not known to have been worshipped,
המאירי Meiri says.
Right right, meaning the this is still this is the presumption. The
presumption is if I find the nose of an idol, it's fine,
no problem, because I assume that even whatever if it came from
was actually an idol, the fact that it's broken means that the
person has... We're going to see. So אמר שמואל אפילו... amar shmuel
afilu... This is very interesting actually.
I was looking over here, and the Steinsaltz has an
image of the
foot, reproduction of a Roman coin with the image of a foot
representing the god Serapis.
There you go, see it's not made up. The rabbis knew what
they were talking about.
אפילו מין בפני עצמו.
afilu
min bifnei atzmo. Meaning, meaning
you find you find this stone right and I want to use,
I want to carve a... building blocks for my house or something,
right.
And that's the point is that and as David was pointing out,
the משנה Mishnah is specifically talking about שברי צלמים, Shivrei Tzelamim, broken
statues, broken images, not necessarily, we don't know for sure that they
were originally used for עבודה זרה, Avoda Zara, just like the first
משנה Mishnah was about whether or not you have to assume a
certain statue is a statue of עבודה זרה Avoda Zara or just
a decorative statue. Here, broken pieces of statues, do you have to
assume they're עבודה זרה Avoda Zara or not? And the assumption is
even if it started off עבודה זרה, Avoda Zara, you assume that
once it's broken, it doesn't matter.
I would say it depends where you find it, you know what
I mean?
Well, the משנה Mishnah doesn't say that.
No, but I'm saying, wouldn't you think? Like, you know, if you
find it in like the garbage dump with the rest of the
rotten banana peels and whatever, as opposed to just like finding it...
so we're going to see why. We're going to see why. And
it's something should remind you of the מדרש Midrash about אברהם אבינו.
Avraham Avinu. So the גמרא Gemara says, אמר שמואל, Amar Shmuel, שמואל
Shmuel said אפילו שברי עבודת כוכבים, Afilu Shivrei Avodat Kochavim, even if
they're broken pieces of what you know to be sure was worshipped
as an idol. והא אנן תנן Ve-ha-anan Tenan שברי צלמים, Shivrei Tzelamim,
but doesn't our משנה Mishnah say specifically only broken pieces of statues?
That is ambiguous statues, not necessarily that they were used for idols?
I guess צלמים Tzelamim is more broad, if צלמים Tzelamim including whatever...
right.
Meaning there's no prohibition of צלמים Tzelamim unless you know that they're
עבודה זרה, Avoda Zara, right? Just a statue is not problematic. So
הוא הדין דאפילו שברי עבודת כוכבים. Hu ha-din de-afilu shivrei avodat kochavim.
So שמואל Shmuel just says no, the משנה Mishnah really means to
include even specifically broken idols as well. והא דקתני שברי צלמים, Ve-ha
de-katani shivrei tzelamim, the fact that it says specifically or less specifically
broken statues משום דקבעי למתני סיפא, mishum de-ka-ba'ei le-matni seifa,
because it makes sense to set it up for the end of
the משנה, Mishnah, which is a reference to the foot and the
hand, which even if they come from a statue, you have to
assume that once they're only the foot or the hand, that is,
even if I don't know for sure that it came from an
עבודה זרה Avoda Zara source, if it's ambiguous, still those are prohibited
as well. So it's a setup. Very often we see this with
משניות, Mishnayot, the first half sets up the second half in different
ways, and therefore they're meant to go together. So מצא תבנית יד
תבנית רגל, Matza tavnit yad, tavnit regel, if I found a hand
or a foot, הרי אלו אסורים מפני שכיוצא בהן נעבד. harei elu
asurim mipnei she-kayotze bahen ne'evad. Those are prohibited because things like that
are worshipped. תנן מצא תבנית יד תבנית רגל הרי אלו אסורין. Tenan:
matza tavnit yad, tavnit regel, harei elu asurin. It taught that the
shape of a hand and shape of a foot are prohibited if
you find them מפני שכיוצא בו נעבד mipnei she-kayotze bo ne'evad
because like those are worshipped. אמאי? Amai? So why is it? Turn
the page. והא שברים נינהו? Ve-ha shevarim ninhu? But aren't they broken
pieces? תרגמה שמואל... Targema Shmuel...
so that is, broken pieces of something which is even from a...
so that is, it comes to subvert or to limit the parameters
of the first teaching in the משנה, Mishnah, that is broken pieces
of statues are permissible except for feet and hands.
Don't try to understand it. So if you found just like a
regular statue's hand and foot that you know wasn't worshipped, you're saying
it's still אסור assur because it's...
No, but how do you know? How do you know it's a
broken statue? I don't know what it came from.
No, but he's saying that הוא הדין דאפילו, Hu ha-din de-afilu, I'm
just going back. הוא הדין דאפילו שברי עבודה זרה והא דקתני שברי
צלמים...
Hu ha-din de-afilu shivrei avoda zara ve-ha de-katani
shivrei tzelamim...
No, that they would be permissible.
No, סיפא, Seifa, מצא תבנית יד... matza tavnit yad...
Right, it's taught דקבעי למתני סיפא, de-ka-ba'ei le-matni seifa, it comes to
teach that the ones... right, that so I guess the point is
that someone may get for themselves a foot of a statue that
used to be worshipped לנוי le-noy and then start worshipping that foot
even after it's broken.
But that's interesting.
Right. Yeah. Because it doesn't have to have been made to be
עבודה זרה Avoda Zara from the beginning, as soon as someone worships
it, right?
תרגמה שמואל, Targema Shmuel, שמואל Shmuel said further בעומדים על בסיסן. Be-omdim
al besisan. Specifically... בעומדים על בסיסן... Be-omdim al besisan... no, sorry, בעומדים
על
בסיסן... Be-omdim al besisan... it's while they're still attached to the base.
That is, if it's a foot on a base, I think specifically,
the hand probably was never attached to the base, but the foot,
if it's still attached to the base, that's when you can assume
that it was a broken-off, a broken piece of a statue
that could still be worshipped because it's sort of on the statue,
on the statue base. You know how there's like a, whatever, pedestal
or whatever that the statue is made on, so they're out of
a pedestal.
You could have just a pedestal beneath your foot.
I draw a
pedestal beneath my foot, it's very poetic.
Right. It's on a base, so I can do cubes better than
I can do feet. Okay. איתמר, Itmar, עבודת כוכבים שנשברה מאליה. Avodat
kochavim she-nishbera me-eileha. What about an idol that breaks on its own?
I assume in an earthquake or something fell on it, it fell
over. Well, we're going to see the דגון Dagon case is coming
up, don't worry, everyone's familiar with their תנ"ך, Tanakh, it's good. Okay.
So עבודת כוכבים שנשברה מאליה, Avodat kochavim she-nishbera me-eileha,
if it broke on its own, רבי יוחנן אמר אסורה, Rabbi Yochanan
amar: asura, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says prohibited, וריש לקיש אמר מותרת.
ve-Reish Lakish amar: muteret. So מחלוקת machloket between ריש לקיש Reish Lakish
and רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
whether it's permissible or not. That is, we said שברי כלים... shivrei
kelim... שברי צלמים shivrei tzelamim are permissible,
is it only if... the question is, is it because... because it's
broken or is it because someone broke it? Those are the questions.
Okay, so אמר רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan אמר אסורה *amar Rabbi Yochanan
amar asura*, רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* says it's prohibited, why? דהא לא
בטלה *deha lo batla*, because no person ever came along to nullify
its status as עבודה זרה avodah zarah. *avoda zara*. That is, we
know that non-Jews have the ability to take something which used to
be עבודה זרה *avoda zara* and to be מבטל *mevatel*, to nullify
its standing as an עבודה זרה *avoda zara* and to turn turn
it into regular material again. However, a Jewish person, just as an
important detail, if a Jewish person worships עבודה זרה *avoda zara*, they
have no power to nullify it.
So once a Jewish person bows down to something, then even if
it becomes עבודה זרה *avoda zara* that they worshipped, and then even
if they do תשובה *teshuva* and they try to be מבטל *mevatel*
or whatever, the object retains the עבודה זרה *avoda zara* status. So
that's a stringency by Jews compared to non-Jews. But non-Jews have the
ability to be מבטל *mevatel*, to undo the עבודה זרה *avoda zara*
status. So רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* says a person has to have
come along and declared either mentally or through their action of breaking
the object to say, "Oh, this is not an idol anymore." רבי
שמעון בן לקיש אומר מותרת *Rabbi Shimon ben Lakish omer muteret*. ריש
לקיש *Reish Lakish* says it's permissible. מסתמא ביטולי מבטלה *mistama bituli mevatla*
because you could assume or because once it is broken, you presume
that the person will no longer worship it, that they'll have in
mind that this isn't going to be a useful idol for them
anymore. Why?
Reminds me reminds me like יאוש שלא מדעת *yei'ush shelo mada'at*.
It's almost like a יאוש שלא מדעת *yei'ush shelo mada'at* kind of
thing, that is, we can presume that the person no longer cares
about it. Why? מימר אמר אי נפשיה לא אצלה לההוא גברא אצלה
*meimar amar i nafshei lo atzlah le-hahu gavra atzlah* because it couldn't
even save itself from being
broken, is it going to be able to save this person? That
is talking about themselves. That is and that's a story that that's
how אברהם Avraham, *Avraham* tried to convince his father not to worship
idols, because he said, right? The big according to the מדרש *Midrash*
anyway. Right, according to the מדרש *Midrash*, obviously. But that he was
the big idol is holding the staff and he broke all of
the other idols. And his father comes in and says like, you
know, "How is it that all the idols are broken?" He says,
"Oh, the big one broke them all because he didn't get food
first," or whatever, right? And תרח *Terach* says you're speaking total nonsense.
You think these idols can just go around and breaking everything? And
אברהם Avraham *Avraham* says, "So why do you worship them, right? ולא
ישמעו אזנך מה שמוציא מפיך *v'lo yishm'u oznecha mah she'motzi mipicha*. Your
ears should hear what's coming out of your mouth." So that's this
kind of point. That is, to a certain extent, and again, and
this gets back into the question which many of the נביאים *nevi'im*
raise and how laughable is עבודה זרה *avoda zara*, how simplistic is
their belief. I think, to a certain extent, ריש לקיש *Reish Lakish*
is taking it maybe a little bit too far. That is, I
doubt if very many intelligent worshippers of עבודה זרה *avoda zara* actually
think that the idol itself has any powers or any ability to
do anything in the world. The problem of עבודה זרה *avoda zara*
is not that you think that a piece of stone is God.
The problem is that you think that it's permissible to make a
piece of stone into the shape of God and and worship it
as if it's God or a representative of God. That's the problem.
So here, the rhetoric is a little bit sharp. He's borrowing the
rhetoric from the נביאים *nevi'im*, הושע *Hoshea* and and ישעיהו *Yeshayahu* and
others.
Obviously, it's very powerful rhetoric, but it doesn't exactly capture the real
psychology involved with people who worship עבודה זרה *avoda zara*. Anyway, okay.
איתיביה רבי יוחנן לריש לקיש *itiviya Rabbi Yochanan l'Reish Lakish*. So רבי
יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* tries to challenge ריש לקיש's *Reish Lakish's* position to
what case? Exactly the case of דגון Dagon, *Dagon*. דגון Dagon? *Dagon*,
דגון *Dagon*. There's a question: is דגון *Dagon* a fish or is
דגון *Dagon* based on grain? Or is it not even a Semitic
root at all? It's maybe from an Indo-European language. We don't know.
Did the פלשתים *Plishtim* come from Crete? Who knows? There are all
sorts of different things. So וראש דגון ושתי כפות ידיו
כרותות
*v'rosh Dagon u'shtei kappot yadav kerutot*. Right, the דגון *Dagon* statue in...
it was in גת *Gat*, right? The פלשתים *Plishtim* took the the
ארון *aron* to the city of גת *Gat* and they brought it
into the temple of their idol.
And then every day, right, the statue fell over and the statue
it was broken. The head fell off and the two palms of
its hand fell off. וכתיב על כן לא ידרכו כהני דגון *u'chtiv
al kein lo yidrechu kohanei Dagon*. And after the idol was destroyed,
the priests of דגון *Dagon* were still called the priests of דגון
*Dagon*. That is, their faith was un- their belief in this idolatry
was unflinching, even in the face of the idol having been destroyed.
That is, you ריש לקיש *Reish Lakish*, your presumption that, "Oh, the
people will say, 'Oh, the idol couldn't even save itself from being
broken, so that it's not it won't save me,'" is obviously not
a correct assumption about how people think about their עבודה זרה *avoda
zara*. אמר לו *amar lo* משום ראיה *mishum re'aya*? You're going to
bring a proof from there? התם שמניחין את הדגון ועובדים את המפתן
*hatam she-manichin et ha-Dagon v'ovdim et ha-miftan*.
The reason is because they stop worshipping דגון *Dagon* and they start
worshipping a different a different idol. דאמרי הכי שבקי איסורי לדגון *d'amri
hachi shavkei isurei l'Dagon*
because they sort of assume that
isn't the מפתן *miftan* like the what's it called?
The מפתן *miftan*, the lintel? The threshold. The lintel, what, of the,
of the beam, the beam of, right, the threshold? Because דגון smashed
it, right? So this is again the mindset of אברהם, right? אברהם
himself, his first thought, right, was, oh, נמרוד Nimrod worships the fire,
but he says, wait, but water can put out the fire, so
maybe I should worship the water. But he says the sun can
dry out the water, right? So this is the same mindset, right?
The doorstep of the temple where the idol broke, so they say
they stop worshipping דגון, but they start worshipping the doorstep which broke
it. They don't have a sense that actually הקדוש ברוך הוא Hakadosh
Baruch Hu is in charge of everything and it made the idol
fall over. They just say, oh, well, what broke the statue must
have been the the doorway. Okay,
so,
okay. Fish,
right, no, so but that's there's that's from the and you're looking
at Artscroll Artscroll's drawing on from the from רש''י Rashi in particular
and other מדרשים Midrashim suggest it was based on fish. As far
as I understand, it may not necessarily be related to fish, but
certainly there is such an interpretation and certainly, you know, I don't
know, I haven't excav- I haven't gone excavating Philistine cities to know
what their idols looked like, so I don't know.
Okay.
Mentioned widely throughout the Middle East, which means it probably would be
a Semitic, what, דגון? Yeah, but it might be grain.
It certainly makes more sense to have a grain god than a
fish god, I mean, but none of it makes any sense, I
don't- doesn't have to make sense. Yeah, this is מוזר, Mozar, it
doesn't make sense. Okay. So, okay. איתיבי, Eitvei, he's challenged him again.
המוציא שברי צלמים, hamotzi shivrei tzelamim, someone who finds broken pieces of
statues, הרי אלו מותרין, harei elu mutarin, they are permissible. הא שברי
עבודה כוכבים אסורין, ha shivrei avodah kochavim asurin, you could infer from
that that if you knew for sure that it used to be
actually worshipped, not just statues, but really worshipped idol, that it would
be prohibited. So לא תימא lo teima שברי עבודה כוכבים אסורין, shivrei
avodah kochavim asurin, you shouldn't say that broken pieces of idols are
prohibited, אלא אימא ela eima הצלמים עצמן אסורין, hatzelamim atzman asurin,
no, that statues you could infer also that whole complete statues even
if you don't know if they're worshipped are also prohibited. וסתמא כרבי
מאיר, u'stama k'Rabbi Meir, and this משנה Mishnah follows the opinion of
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir from the last משנה. Mishnah. ורבי יוחנן v'Rabbi
Yochanan מדרבי מאיר נשמע להו לרבנן. mi'd'Rabbi Meir nishma lehu l'Rabbanan. רבי
יוחנן
can infer the opinion of the רבנן Rabbanan of the of the
middle position of the previous משנה, Mishnah, that is holding the bird,
holding the whatever, infers it from רבי מאיר's Rabbi Meir position. So
לאו אמר lav amar רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir צלמים אסורין, tzelamim asurin,
didn't רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir say that that statues
are prohibited? שברי צלמים מותרין, shivrei tzelamim mutarin, then broken statues should
be permissible. לרבנן l'Rabbanan עבודה כוכבים, avodah kochavim,
so according to the רבנן, Rabbanan, that previous משנה Mishnah must have
been about, not about סתם צלמים, stam tzelamim, any statues, but specifically
about idols.
So נמי אסורה ושברים מותרין, nami asura u'shevarim mutarin, so so too
we could infer that even if you know for sure that it
was worshipped, according to רבנן, Rabbanan, only is prohibited if you know
for sure it was worshipped or you have a strong presumption that
it was worshipped, so then even those when they're broken would be
permissible according to רבנן. Rabbanan. So הכי השתא? hachi hashta? התם אימא
עבדום, hatam eima avudum, so you were saying, oh, it's because they
worship them. אימא לא עבדום, eima lo avudum,
but what about a case where they weren't worshipped? ואם תמצי לומר
עבדום, v'im timtzei lomar avudum, but if they worshipped them, אימא ביטלום,
eima bitlum, maybe they nullified them. עבודה כוכבים ודאי עבדוה, avodah kochavim
vadai avaduha, if it was clearly built in such a way that
it appears to have been a real idol, then obviously it was
worshipped at some point. So מי אימר דביטלה, mi eimar d'bitla, how
do you know that it was ever cancel- it was ever nullified?
הוי ספק ודאי, havei safeik vadai,
that's a case of a ספק safeik against a ודאי, vadai, that
is, we have a ודאי vadai status, we know for sure that
it was worshipped, it for sure is of the status of עבודה
זרה. And now you're going to try to say ספק, safeik, maybe
it was nullified. So we have a general principle אין ספק מוציא
מידי ודאי, ein safeik motzi midei vadai, a doubtful claim can't extract
you out of a sure sure thing status, right? A doubt can't
get you out of a surety. So here too, ספק ודאי ואין
ספק מוציא מידי ודאי, safeik vadai v'ein safeik motzi midei vadai, a
ספק safeik about whether it was ever בטל batel cannot remove it
from the 100 percent sure status that it was actually made prohibited.
ואין ספק מוציא מידי ודאי, v'ein safeik motzi midei vadai, but is
it really true that ספק safeik can't get you out of a
ודאי? vadai? והתניא, veha tanya, חבר שמת, chaver shemet,
a reliable rabbinic figure who keeps תרומה terumah and מעשר ma'aser and
everything like that, died. והניח מגורה מלאה פירות, vehinnich megurah mlei'ah peirot,
and he left behind a basket full of fruits, אפילו הן בני
יומן, afilu hen bnei yoman, even if they are freshly picked, ripe
that day, הרי הן בחזקת מתוקנים, harei hen b'chezkat metukanim, we can
assume that the תרומה terumah and the מעשר ma'aser have already been
removed.
Okay. והא הכא דודאי טבילי? veha hacha de'vadai tvilei?
Safeik hachi safeik vadai tvilei, or am I,
oh, maybe I somehow skipped, והא הכא דודאי טבילי? veha hacha de'vadai
tvilei?
They are, they were ודאי טבל, vadai tevel they were 100 percent
known to be טבל. tevel, Fresh off the tree, ספק עשרינהו ספק
לא עשרינהו, safeik asrinhu safeik lo asrinhu,
and then you don't actually know whether this חבר chaver right before
he had the heart attack whether he separated תרומה trumah and מעשר
ma'aser from the fruits. וקאתי ספק ומוציא מידי ודאי, v'ka'ati safeik u'motzi
midei vadai, and the principle here is that the ספק safeik of
whether or not he took off the תרומות trumot is enough to
assume that it's good enough. That is, a ספק safeik is מוציא
מידי ודאי. motzi midei vadai. So that case from this case of
separating תרומה trumah sounds like a proof against the principle אין ספק
מוציא מידי ודאי. ein safeik motzi midei vadai. Yeah, Charlie.
Would it depend on where the basket was found because you're not
חייב chayav in מעשר ma'aser until you bring it into your house?
So מעשר ma'aser no, but תרומה trumah even if it's out in
the field. Assuming, let's assume for the moment that it was brought
into the home. He says הניח, hiniach, like he left it behind,
sounds like in his property, in his home when he died. But
if you want to say it was out in the field then
still תרומה trumah you'd have to separate, right?
Okay. So the answer, we have an answer: התם ודאי ודאי הוא
דודאי עשרינהו. hatam vadai vadai hu d'vadai asrinhu. So, no, the חזקה
chazakah that you're a חבר chaver is so strong and this is
very interesting for thinking about how do חזקות chazakot work. How do
these presumptions work? We really do treat many of the חזקות chazakot
as ודאי, vadai 100% surety. That is, ודאי ודאי, vadai vadai, it's
ודאי vadai, against the ודאי. ודאי vadai vadai, טבל tevel. and it's
ודאי vadai that he separated the תרומה, trumah, דודאי עשרינהו. d'vadai asrinhu.
We can 100% assume that a חבר chaver separated תרומה trumah and
מעשר. ma'aser. By the way, there's just something else that I've been
learning towards the beginning of אבן העזר, Even Ha'ezer, some of the
discussion about כהנים Kohanim are of the status only by חזקה. chazakah.
We don't necessarily have a genealogical proof that every כהן Kohen nowadays
goes back all the way to כהנים Kohanim who served in the
Temple. So most כהנים Kohanim we treat them by חזקה. chazakah. They
have a presumption, an assumption that they're כהנים. Kohanim. So, but as
the point is, we still don't allow them to violate any of
the prohibitions of כהונה kehunah as רש"י Rashi and many of the
other ראשונים Rishonim point out in many places
that we're willing to execute people based on חזקות, chazakot, right? How
do I actually do we do a paternity test? Someone punches their
father in the face, they're going to be executed. But do we
have to do a paternity test to prove that the person really
is their father and not someone else? Right, this goes back to
סנהדרין Sanhedrin and other מסכתות. Masechtot. We
חזקות chazakot are strong enough even for capital punishment. We say אין
עונשין מן הדין, ein onshin min hadin, you can't execute people based
on קל וחומר. kal v'chomer. So the level of surety and the
level of judicial weight behind these חזקות chazakot is very strong.
Okay, כדי רבי חנינה חוזאה דאמר רבי חנינה חוזאה. ki d'Rabbi Chanina
Choza'ah d'amar Rabbi Chanina Choza'ah. So Rabbi Chanina from חוזאה Choza'ah said,
חזקה על חבר שאינו מוציא דבר שאינו מתוקן מתחת ידו. chazakah al
chaver she'eino motzi davar she'eino metukan mitachat yado. The assumption about a
חבר chaver is not just that we assume that he will separate
תרומה trumah and מעשר, ma'aser, but actually that he never lets it
leave his hand. I think we could take it very literally. It's
when it's in his control, when it's under his purview, then it
will be מתוקן. metukan. He will separate out תרומה trumah and מעשר.
ma'aser. That's such a high level of presumption about what it means
to be a חבר. chaver. Okay, ואיבעית אימא, v'iba'it eima,
alternatively, how can we understand the case from that ברייתא? Baraita? So
this was attempt number one. We said no, really it's ודאי vadai.
ודאי, vadai right? It's a ודאי טבל vadai tevel against a ודאי
vadai that the חבר chaver was מפריש תרומה. mafrish trumah. ואיבעית אימא,
v'iba'it eima, alternatively, ספק וספק הוא. safeik v'safeik hu.
No, it's actually ספק safeik against a ספק. safeik. So, let's see
what רש"י Rashi says, כי היכא דמספקא לן אם עישרינהו אם לאו,
ki heicha d'misfaka lan im isrinhu im lav,
we don't know whether he separated out מעשר ma'aser or not,
נמי מספקא לן אם היו מעולם טבל אם לאו אע"פ דנגמרה מלאכתן.
nami misfaka lan im hayu me'olam tevel im lav af al gav
d'nigmerah melachtan.
Because we don't know, this is sort of based on Charlie's point,
that we don't know whether the fruits ever reached a point where
they actually would be prohibited
as טבל. tevel. That is, we don't know whether the processing of
the raw produce had been fully accomplished yet. שאפשר דעבד כרבי אושעיא.
she'efshar d'avad k'Rabbi Oshaya. It's possible that he could have done like
רבי אושעיא, Rabbi Oshaya, דאמר מעריים אדם על תבואתו מכניסה במוץ שלה.
d'amar maarim adam al tevu'ato machnisah b'motz shelah.
It's possible for a person to circumvent, to commit a subterfuge against
separating תרומה trumah and מעשר ma'aser by harvesting the fruits with the
מוץ. motz. The מוץ motz is like the chaff, the stems, the
outer hull of the grain, כדי שתהא בהמתו אוכלת ופטורה מן המעשר,
k'dei shetehei behemtu ochelet u'pturah min hamaser,
to be able to feed your animal but not to have to
separate out מעשר. ma'aser. That is, I can take very raw, very
unprocessed grain which has not reached the stage where it's obligated even
to separate out תרומה trumah and certainly מעשר ma'aser and then just
feed it directly to the animals and let the animals deal with
it and I won't have to, so I'll be able to get
more animal feed out of my grain, so I'm saving money. And
that's a permissible רבי אושעיא Rabbi Oshaya says it's permissible for a
person to do this subterfuge, which is very interesting. Dr. Lana Stein-Hein,
a friend of mine, wrote her
doctoral. as actually a bug or a feature of the halakhic system
and in different circumstances the rabbis obviously treat it with different different
perspectives and different parameters. Yeah.
Another possibility is that the produce might be ביכורים *bikurim*.
Okay, so but if it's ביכורים *bikurim* then it's going to be
problematic for another reason.
It's problematic for a different reason.
Right. Okay, but meaning we're not going to assume it's ביכורים *bikurim*.
So this is a totally acceptable הערמה *ha'arama*?
According to רבי אושעיא *Rabbi Oshaya*. I'm not so 100 percent firm
on all the details. We don't live in ארץ ישראל *Eretz Yisrael*
so I'm not as as fresh in all of my זרעים *Zeraim*
things.
Let me see for a second.
What was your question, Matt?
Yeah, this is like
really ex- like whether this is really acceptable. I don't know whether
we actually פוסקין
*pasken* like this position.
I think that we do, as far as I know, but maybe
it may still be a bit of a debate.
I think there's a rabbinic prohibition not to do that.
Well that's some of these questions about what does it mean מערים
*maarim*. מערים *maarim* might mean like according to Torah law it's permissible,
but according to rabbinic law it's not, or it might actually mean
it's totally permissible, but it's against the quote-unquote spirit of the law.
There's a lot of question about how much how much is it
or is it not a Jewish concept the idea of spirit of
the law, is that something only Christians made up and then then
we started copying from them or or who knows. Okay, וכרבי אושעיא
דאמר מערים אדם על תבואתו ומכניסה במוץ שלה כדי שתהא בהמתו אוכלת
ופטורה מן המעשר *U'k'Rabbi Oshaya de'amar maarim adam al tevu'ato u'machnisa b'motz
shela kedei she'tehei behemtu ochelet u'ptura min ha'ma'aser*. ואין ספק מוציא מידי
ודאי safek motzi midei vadai? *Ve'ein safeik motzi midei vadai*. But we
could still uphold the principle of ואין ספק safek מוציא מידי ודאי
vadai? *ve'ein safeik motzi midei vadai*. Well רמב"ם *Rambam* says you actually
could bring it in like, you know, through the roof, right? There's
a lot of discussion in מסכת מעשרות *Masechet Ma'asrot* about bringing through
the roof and all these different things. There's a lot a lot
there,
but sort of and again it sort of gets into the whole
point of like, yeah, but הערמה *ha'arama* like you're try- you do
all of these ridiculous things just in order to save a little
bit of money to avoid doing a מצוה *mitzvah*. It's like very,
you know, משה רבינו *Moshe Rabbeinu* was so upset he didn't get
to go into the land of Israel to do the מצוות התלויות
בארץ *mitzvot hateluyot ba'aretz* and here you are you're intentionally circumventing everything.
So that's why from a religious perspective it's very negative kind of
attitude but whether it's technically permissible or not becomes an important question.
Okay, let's continue. Okay, ואין ספק safek מוציא מידי ודאי vadai *ve'ein
safeik motzi midei vadai*. So that's the point is saying actually since
the produce could have been produce which was never obligated in תרומה
*terumah* and מעשר *ma'aser* anyway, so it's really a ספק safek טבל
*safek tevel*, right? Because the potential always exists, not that we're assuming
that this חבר *chaver* did it, but because the potential exists then
we could have considered that every case of טבל *tevel* is actually
ספק safek. טבל *safek tevel* because you could have done it in
a way it wouldn't become טבל *tevel*. And therefore now it's ספק
וספק *safek v'safek* and therefore you're also safe. But we still maintain
the general principle ואין ספק מוציא מידי ודאי vadai *ve'ein safeik motzi
midei vadai*. Yeah, David.
Yes, so there's a note here saying that רבי אושעיא *Rabbi Oshaya*
is offering this opportunity only for like informal consumption.
Right, but here it's talking it's to feed the animal.
Feeding the animal is not informal consumption.
What? Even טבל *tevel* to animals, you're stealing from the כהן Kohen
*Kohein*.
I can't feed טבל *tevel* to animals.
I think רבי פנחס בן יאיר *Rabbi
Pinchas ben Yair*'s donkey
refused
to eat טבל *tevel*.
Right.
You could feed טבל *tevel* to donkey but only if- but only
if he didn't take it in through the house and everything else,
right. Meaning if it was נגמר מלאכתו *nigmar melachto* if it still-
if it became חייב *chayav* in הפרשה *hafrasha* at whatever point then
you you lock it in and then you have to be מפריש
*mafresh*. So the point here is if you use רבי אושעיא *Rabbi
Oshaya*'s הערמה *ha'arama* to avoid becoming חייב *chayav* then that's exactly the
case. Right. Okay. Okay, last line of מ"א עמוד ב' *Mem Aleph
Amud Bet*. והתניא אמר רבי יהודה *veha tanya amar Rabbi Yehuda*. ואין
ספק מוציא מידי ודאי vadai.
*ve'ein safeik motzi midei vadai*. Where should we be at?
Yeah,
meaning we're still asking further questions on the principle. Right. והתניא *veha
tanya*, but didn't we teach in this ברייתא braita *baraita*, אמר רבי
יהודה מעשה בשפחתה של מציק אחד ברימון שהטילה נפל nefel. לבור *amar
Rabbi Yehuda ma'ase b'shifchatah shel metzik echad b'Rimon she'hetila nefel l'bor*. There
was a case of this שפחה shifcha, *shifcha*, a slave woman,
who was- she was pregnant and she of-
of such a a certain rich woman in Rimon in the north
of Israel שהטילה נפל לבור *she'hetila nefel l'bor* she had a miscarriage
and she put the the fetus into into the
water cistern. ובא כהן Kohen והציץ לידע אם זכר אם נקבה leida
im zachar im nekeivah, *u'va Kohein ve'heitzitz leida im zachar im nekeiva*.
And a כהן Kohen. *Kohein* came to kind of like peek and
see whether it was a boy or a girl who had- that
she had had the miscarriage. Okay. ובא מעשה לפני חכמים וטיהרוהו *u'va
ma'ase lifnei Chachamim ve'tiharuhu*. And the rabbis came and actually declared that
this כהן *Kohein* is still טהור *tahor*, that he even though he
came very close to coming in contact with the air space of
the corpse, but nonetheless the rabbis declared him טהור *tahor* מפני שחולדה
ובר *mipnei she'chulda u'var*. because there are weasels and whatever other kind
of whatever it is
hedgehogs or whatever kind of polecats I don't know what exactly what
kind of animals these are but they're the kind of animals that
could take—just saw an
Aramaic word coming up for a leopard-like beast. A leopard?
I don't think it's a leopard. It's something else in this context.
Anyway, anyway, it's an animal that would come and and come and
take would take the fetus away. That is, she had thrown it
into the בור, bor, the כהן went to try to peak to
see whether what was in the בור, bor and then the rabbis
said, no, no, no, because there are חולדות chuldot around here and
and there are animals that could have come to take the body,
we can assume that at least it was a ספק whether he
actually became טמא. tamei. מצויין שם והא איכא דודאי הטילה נפל metzuyim
sham ve-ha ika de-vadai hitila nefel but she definitely threw the the
fetus in the בור bor and ספק גיררוהו ספק לא גיררוהו safek
giraruhu safek lo giraruhu but it's a doubtful whether or not an
animal actually took away the body וקאתי ספק ומוציא מידי ודאי ve-ka'ati
safek u-motzi midei vadai and the rabbis came and said—Question.
Right, that's the question.
Meaning, doesn't it sound like here a ספק did beat a ודאי?
So here, so far, our first two cases were, oh, maybe you
could explain it's ודאי and ודאי and maybe you could explain it's
ספק and ספק. That was for the first ברייתא that challenged this
principle, and now we have this
case. Okay. So לא תימא הטילה נפל
לבור אלא אימא הטילה כמין נפל לבור. lo teima hitila nefel la-bor
ela eima hitila ke-min nefel la-bor. She threw something into the בור
bor. which maybe was a נפל. If you learn מסכת אהלות Masechet
Ohalot and מסכת נדה, Masechet Niddah, there's an extensive discussion of at
what stage—This came up,
this came up a bunch of times.
It comes up in many times, this particular case. Right, even this
case, so right, it's in פסחים, Pesachim, it's in נדה, Niddah, so
so there are stages of fetal development at what point and certainly
if if whatever the woman sees as this miscarriage is something which
which is very inhuman in its form or in its development. Obviously,
various kinds of developmental defects and things, obviously that the pregnancy would
not be viable, but those kinds of things at a certain extent
it's no longer considered to be מטמא metamei like a human corpse
because it's actually seen as some other kind of other kind of
it's of a lower level טומאה tumah because it's not seen as
a human body, it's seen as something that came out of the
human body, it's seen as like a piece of skin or a
piece of of tissue but not not a an actual body. Okay.
Sorry, it's very difficult to like—Yeah. It's very—these are very tragic kinds
of things and obviously comes up in these סוגיות sugyot in very
very flat—it's just, oh, it's just a legal case like everything else.
But—I wonder if the woman was Jewish or not. I mean—I don't
think it matters
whether she's a Jewish woman or not.
Here she's a שפחה, shifcha so שפחה is again is kind of
borderline, but it doesn't matter because generally it's a bit of a
מחלוקת תנאים machloket tanna'im but basically we treat the Jewish and non-Jewish
מתים metim are are both מטמא metamei of the same status. Okay.
So isn't this a case of ספק מוציא מידי ודאי? לא תימא
הטילה נפל לבור אלא אימא הטילה כמין נפל. lo teima hitila nefel
la-bor ela eima hitila ke-min nefel. Something that resembled a fetus. והא
לידע אם זכר אם נקבה הוא דקתני. ve-ha leida im zachar im
nekeivah hu de-katani. But it says that the כהן went to go
see if it was male or female, that is, it sounds like
it had enough of a human form that he would be able
have been to tell—הכי קאמר לידע אם רוח הפילה אם נפל הטילה.
hachi ka'amar leida im ruach hepila im nefel hitila. To see what
and you can actually see the difference in the verb as well.
אם רוח הפילה, im ruach hepila, if it was a living that
is a living human being הפילה hepila that she had a miscarriage,
והאם נפל הטילה, ve-im nefel hitila, and if it was the that
is if it was—sorry, רוח, ruach, that it was nothing or if
the miscarriage was of a real human something or something of a
lower status. והאם נפל הטילה. ve-im nefel hitila. And if it was
the actually the miscarriage, the fetus that she threw into the בור.
bor, ואם תמצי לומר נפל הטילה, ve-im timtzi lomar nefel hitila, and
then even if you'll say that she actually did throw a fetus
into the בור, bor, לידע אם זכר אם נקבה, and then it
was to see whether it was male or female. Male or—it doesn't
make a difference. Why was he looking for that? I don't know.
Now I would think that maybe she was Jewish and it has
to do with her with the
lady's טומאה tumah status.
For her טומאה tumah status. Yes, right. Because she'll have, right,
right, she'll have one week or two weeks and 33 days and
66 days.
I didn't think of that right now, you're right. Maybe she was
a כהנת. Kohenet. Right, that's a good question too. They should have
sent someone who's not a כהן. Maybe he was the smartest one
around. Maybe or whatever, he was the one who knew what a
boy or a girl
looks like at an early on in fetal development.
Everyone looks like a girl. So that's also—anyway, ואיבעית אימא כיון שחולדה
וברדלס מצויין שם ודאי גיררוהו.
ve-iba'it eima keivan she-chuldah
u-vardelas metzuyim sham vadai giraruhu. Maybe you could actually say that since
there are these animals around, actually we treat it as a ודאי.
That these kinds of scavenging animals are so so prevalent to to
take any kind of, you know, I can't say it but like
any kind of meat that they could get to eat that— They
would even take, they would for sure, if she had thrown it
into the בור, they would have for sure taken it. So it's
not a good proof that we discount the principle of אין ספק
מוציא מידי ודאי. ein safek motzi midei vaday. This will be continued
on tomorrow's דף. daf. Hope everyone has a great day, and I
think Jenna is going to be teaching tomorrow. All right, bye-bye.